## AHMED L. RASHED

Columbus, OH 43204 | 781-309-7560 | LinkedIn Profile | GitHub Portfolio | arashed07@gmail.com

### **Professional Summary**

Highly analytical and **process-oriented** data wrangler with over 10 years of experience in **data mining, statistical analysis, business intelligence gathering, trending, and benchmarking**. Created **ML models** on device telemetry to **pre-emptively classify CTQ** device failures before Final Test, *cutting rework times by 25%* and *increasing throughput by 10%*. Collaborated with test engineers to develop **ETL processes** to facilitate the **movement of data** between systems, **identifying patterns and insights** in the data, *reducing failure rates from 35% to 2%*.

#### **Technical Skills**

**Data Analytics:** SQL, R Programming, Python, Tableau, Power BI (PowerQuery, DAX), Statistics, Hypothesis Testing. **Machine Learning:** Linear/Logistic Regression, GridSearchCV, Random-Forest, XGBoost, Decision-Trees, Time-Series. **Database & Project Management:** EDA, ETL, SQL Server, Azure Data Studio, Google BigQuery, Agile, Scrum, JIRA, Git. **Business Intelligence:** Collaboration, Continuous Improvement, Data Cleaning, Data Visualization, Data Presentation, Requirement Gathering, Problem Solving, Root-Cause Analysis, Turning Questions into Queries and Data into Insights.

# **Work Experience**

Data Analytics Consultant

**HENNY PENNY** 

REMOTE- OH

11/2022 - 08/2023

Implemented **data hooks** in production test stand software to identify **key metrics** and **transform raw data** into meaningful, **actionable information** through **automated extraction** and **standardized reporting**.

- Created various **Python scripts** (numpy, pandas) using **SQL** (complex joins) to **extract and analyze** factory data, enhancing build quality and *saving Mfg engineers over 15 hours each week* in manual data manipulation.
- Collaborated with test engineers to develop **ETL processes** to facilitate the **movement of data** between systems, **identifying patterns and insights** in the data, *reducing failure rates from 35% to 2%.*

**Key Project:** Created python utility to extract and transform data from TestStand SQL database schema into flat CSV files.

- o **Tools Used:** SQL Server Management Studio, T-SQL, Python, PYODBC, Pandas.
- Results: Reduced script to single-file, used auto-py-to-exe to build a stand-alone executable file for users to download.

*Ouality Engineer Consultant* 

**GRANVILLE PHILLIPS** 

**REMOTE-CO** 

09/2022 - 01/2023

Developed and integrated **data-driven metrics** into existing TestStand system to optimize Mfg process.

- Implemented **Python predictive analytics** (Scikit-learn) on test-unit data streams to **pre-emptively classify CTQ** device faults before Final Test, *cutting rework times by 25%* and *increasing throughput by 10%*.
- Deployed Mfg Statistical-Process-Control dashboards, improving first-pass-yield rates from 75% to 95%.

Principal Test Engineer

**MKS INSTRUMENTS** 

Methuen, MA

03/2021 - 06/2022

Managed test station software projects, **ensuring quality and reliability** of software through comprehensive **testing and analysis**. Picked up **Python** and **SQL** on-the-job to drive enhanced **data analysis and visualization** for Tech Ops and Business Unit teams, creating compelling **data-driven reports** to upper management.

- Extracted and extrapolated Mfg data using **Python, SQL, and Excel** for monthly **quality reports**, *preventing over* \$50,000 in lost annual revenue by catching product quality defects BEFORE they leave the factory floor.
- Developed **ARIMA models** to fit and forecast **time series data** of production **workstation/kiosk telemetry**. Deployed these models to **interactive time series plots** and dashboards for Production Managers and Supply Chain Managers.
- Designed and built statistical analysis models on large data sets using Azure Data Studio that helped reduce product rework and post-processing test-time by 15%.

Senior Test Engineer

MKS INSTRUMENTS

Methuen, MA

09/2011 - 02/2021

Incorporated extensive upgrading and overhauling legacy product lines. Rewrote test software architecture into **robust, data-driven, user-friendly applications**, *improving quality, reliability, and efficiency*.

- Connected **Tableau dashboards** to centralized **data-pipeline** for real-time production **data tracking**, *improving average time-to-bug-fixes by 20%* and *highlighting time-sinks* in factory workflows.
- Created **visually impactful dashboards** and **executive data visualizations** in Tableau to track production yields and failure modes, *saving test engineers over 10 hours* weekly in diagnostics and manual reporting.
- Implemented **data quality monitoring** tools to **automatically identify and flag anomalies** or errors in data. Setup database access based on job roles and responsibilities, *preventing unauthorized usage and potential breaches*.

Test Engineer

#### **MKS INSTRUMENTS**

Methuen, MA

06/2008 - 08/2011

Sustained production by creating and updating test software, troubleshooting test stand issues and malfunctions. Maintained test software to ensure the quality of products, resolving stand problems to keep production moving.

- Kaizen blitz to find root causes of test failures; evaluated corrective actions using Cpk and KPI characterizations.
- **Standardized data collection** and storage, **deconstructing data silos** and enabling **seamless data sharing** across departments, *improving pressure sensor* and *flow meter production yield from 88% to 95%*.

### **Data Projects**

#### TikTok Video Classification:

TVC GitHub Link

12/2023

Built and optimized a predictive logistic model classify TikTok videos as claim vs opinion.

- o Tools Used: Jupyter Notebook, Pandas, Pathlib, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Scikit-learn, Statsmodels.
- o **Approach:** Plot histograms and heat-maps of various metrics of user engagement to determine most correlated variables in the data. Split, train, and test data, creating a confusion matrix to visualize the results of the model.
- o **Results:** Both **RandomForest** and **XGBoost** architectures provided near-perfect models, but **RandomForest** had slightly higher accuracy and less processing. The most predictive features were related to video engagements.

## **Housing Prediction Model:**

HPM GitHub Link

0/2023

Built and optimized a predictive regression model of housing prices with historical CA housing data.

- o **Tools Used:** Jupyter Notebook, Pandas, Pathlib, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Scikit-learn.
- Approach: Identified and removed **outliers** from the dataset. Created and modified the attributes of the data (**feature engineering**) to input into the model that is most relevant to **predicting median-house-value**. Tweaked and tuned Linear, GridSearchCV, and RandomForest Regressions to achieve 83% accurate predictions.
- o **Results:** Evaluated **RandomForest Regression** as the best overall model to predict median-house-value.

#### **COVID-19 Retrospective:**

Cov19 GitHub Link

09/2023

Explored and visualized COVID's most affected countries, highest death rates, and fastest vaccination rates.

- Tools Used: Azure Data Studio, T-SQL, Tableau, Interactive Data Visualization.
- Approach: Explored and sliced the dataset with various SQL queries. Exported tables to CSV files for later importing to Tableau Desktop. After exporting and visualizing, we discovered an error in the calculations. Had to go back and reformat our query to use people\_vaccinated instead of new or total vaccinations.
- o **Results:** Published visualization to **Tableau Public LINK**.

### **Bike Sharing Analysis:**

BSA GitHub Link

07/2023

Exploratory data analysis to identify key metrics and trends to inform and drive appropriate marketing strategy.

- o Tools Used: R, RStudio, Data Extraction, Data Cleaning, Data Transforming, Data Interpretation.
- Approach: Scraped the public data sets from the AWS S3 bucket. Loaded the CSV files with fread() and use rbindlist() to merge the individual data sets together. Transformed data by adding calculated columns. Generated aggregate descriptive statistics of categorical and numerical comparisons to identify A vs B populations.
- o **Results:** Minor **trends** in weekday vs weekend usage. Exported data for further time-series analysis.

### **Education & Certification**

Google Advanced Data Analytics Certificate

Google Data Analytics Certificate

Master of Arts - Physics - Bryn Mawr College

**Bachelor of Science -** *Applied Physics -* UMBC